A Guide to the L. Sterling Wortman papers FA1121
Rockefeller Archive Center
L. Sterling Wortman papers
1950, 1956, 1958-1959, 1964-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wortman, Sterling (1923-1981)
Rockefeller Foundation
FA1121
4.27 Cubic Feet 10 letter document boxes and 1 legal document box
Arrangement
Original Order
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Sterling Wortman began his career with the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) as a plant geneticist with the Mexican Agricultural Program (MAP). He went on to become a leading figure in the Foundation's efforts to establish international agricultural research institutes in the 1960s and 1970s.
Wortman was born in Quinlan, Oklahoma on April 3, 1923. He earned his B.S. in agronomy from Oklahoma State University (1943) and Ph.D. in plant breeding and genetics from the University of Minnesota (1950). In 1950, Wortman was hired as a corn breeder in the Mexican Agricultural Program's corn improvement program. He left the MAP in 1955 to head the Plant Breeding Department at the Pineapple Research Institute in Honolulu, Hawaii, and returned to the RF in 1960.
In the 1960s and 1970s the Rockefeller and Ford Foundations collaborated in creating several international agricultural research institutes to carry out MAP's pioneering agricultural work on a global scale. Wortman played a central role in these efforts. He helped launch the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) in the Philippines, focused on researching and re-engineering the rice plant to increase rice production, and served as the IRRI's Assistant Director (1960-1962) and Associate Director (1962-1964). In his 1992 book An Adventure in Applied Science: A History of the International Rice Research Institute, IRRI Founding Director Robert F. Chandler, Jr. emphasized that "Wortman's contribution to the progress of IRRI in those early years cannot be overestimated."
The Foundation's success with IRRI spurred the development of additional international agricultural institutes and organizations. After his appointment as the RF's Director for Agricultural Sciences in 1966, Wortman helped reorganize the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT) in Mexico as private corporation. The move dramatically improved the Center's funding and efficacy. He helped establish the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) in 1971, which served to mobilize and coordinate public and private funding for international research centers. And after becoming a RF Vice-President in 1970, Wortman helped establish the International Agricultural Development Service (IADS), which worked to strengthen agricultural programs in developing nations. He served as the President of IADS from 1975 to 1979.
Wortman assumed the role of the Foundation's Acting President after the death of President John H. Knowles in March 1979. He left his full-time work with the RF after Stanford University President Richard W. Lyman was appointed President in 1980.
Sterling Wortman died of cancer in 1981 at the age of 58.
Scope and Contents
Type of records include: Reports, publications, newspaper articles, correspondence, reprints, speeches, and a manuscript
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection was donated to the RAC by Ruth Worman, wife of Sterling Wortman, in 1982.
- Office Files, 1950, 1956, 1958-1959, 1964-1965, 1967-1969, 1972-1981; 1; 3.13 Cubic Feet 7 letter document boxes and 1 legal document box
  - Rolodex, NY Office, 1974 October 15, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research, Inc. (BTI), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical (CIAT), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Centro Internacional de Mejoramiento de Maiz Y Trigo (CIMMYT), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Centro Internacional de Mejoramiento de Maiz Y Trigo (CIMMYT), Publications, 1976-1977, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Centro Internacional de la Papa (CIP) (International Potato Center), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - International Agricultural Development Service (IADS), 1977, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - International Agricultural Development Service (IADS), Pamphlets, 1976, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - International Development Research Centre (IDRC), 1975, 1977, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - International Food Policy Research Institute (IFPRI), 1977, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA), 1977, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - International Service for National Agricultural Research (ISNAR), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Japan, 1978, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Charles F. Kettering Foundation, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Monell Chemical Senses Center, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Nepal, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, Work, 1973, 1975, 1977, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - U. S. Aid, 1980 June 10 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - World Bank, 1973, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Dominican Republic, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - People's Republic of China, 1972, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - People's Republic of China, Negatives and Slides, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Taiwan, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Situation, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Foreign Investment, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Business People, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Inflation, 1980 June 22 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Productivity (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Trade, 1980 December 11 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Business International Corporation, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Booker Agricultural International (BAI) (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - IBEC, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Monetary, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Biology, Reprints by the Pioneer Research Staff, 1972, 1974, 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Population, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Development Oriented Crops Literature, 1976, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Technical Advisory Committee, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Borlaug, Norman E., 1965, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Harrar, George, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Ponnamperuma, F. N., 1980 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Ruttan, Vernon W., 1977, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Schultz, Theodore W., 1964, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Wharton, Clifton R., Jr., 1980 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Wittwer, Sylvan H., 1975, 1978, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - International Agricultural Development Service (IADS), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - International Agricultural Development Service (IADS), Assistance Agencies, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - International Agricultural Development Service (IADS), Assistance Services, 1974-1975, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - International Agricultural Development Service (IADS), Indicators, 1978, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, By-laws, 1976, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, Fellowships, 1980 April (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, Programs, 1970, 1974, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, Agricultural Science Reports, 1970 November (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Consultant Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR), 1969, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Chile, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Colombia, 1958-1959, 1972, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - India, 1969, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Mexico, 1950, 1956, 1969, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Thailand, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Turkey, 1968, 1972, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Small Farmers, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Scientific American, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - The Strategy of Agricultural Development, 1970 March 28 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - 7: Reaching the Farmer, 1967 September 30 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Chapter 15: Toward More Effective Assistance, 1972, 1974, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - National Science Foundation, 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 68-70)
  - National Science Foundation, 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 69A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from access-Confidential material
- Publications and Speeches, 1964-1981; 2; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
  - "International Agricultural Development", In Honor of John Milton Poehlman, Columbia, MO, 1980 October 21 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Presidential Commission on World Hunger, 1978 December 18 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Address, Food Editors of America, Rye, NY, 1978 November 1 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - "Horticulture's Third Era", 75th Annual Meeting of American Society of Horticultural Science, Boston, MA, 1978 July 17, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - "Accelerating Agricultural Development: The Challenge, The Strategy", IMC Food Production Conference, Santo Domingo, DR, 1977 November 8 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - "Accelerating Agricultural Development", Coromandel Lecture, New Delhi, India, 1977 February 8 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - "The Alleviation of World Hunger", National Council of Philanthropy 22nd Annual Conference, St. Louis, MO, 1976 December 2 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - "The Alleviation of World Hunger", Amended, 2nd Presbyterian Church Series, Indianapolis, IN, 1976 October 6 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - "Food and Agriculture", Scientific American, 1976 September (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - "Agricultural Research: The Emerging World Network", Wageningen Symposium, The Netherlands, 1976 June 16-18 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - "The World Food Situation and Technical Assistance", Stillwater, OK, 1976 April 22 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - "Strategy for the Alleviation of World Hunger", Rochester, NY, 1976 April 12 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Extemporaneous Address, North Pacific Grain Growers, Inc. Annual Meeting, Portland,OR, 1976 February 13 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - "World Crop Productivity: Challenges to Science", International Conference on Crop Productivity: Research Imperatives, Lansing, MI, 1975 October 20 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Plant Studies in the People Republic of China, A Trip Report of the American Plant Studies Delegation, National Academy of Science, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - "The World Food Situation: A New Initiative", U. S. House of Representatives Testimony, 1975 September 23 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - "Agriculture in China", Scientific American, 1975 June (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - "Impact of International Research on the Performance and Objectives of National Systems", Warrenton, VA, 1975 January 26-29 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - "World Food Needs and Opportunities: The Overview", American Society of Agronomy 66th Annual Meeting, Chicago, IL, 1974 November 12 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - "The Rural Development System of the People's republic of China: Impressions and Questions", 1974 November (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - "Food, Resource Use, and International Agriculture", 15th Anniversary Celebration of Texas Tech University, Lubbock, TX, 1974 October 17 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - "The Yield Gap: The World's Great Food Reserve", Annual Meeting of the Agricultural Research Institute, Denver, CO, 1974 October 15 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Strengthening National Agricultural Research, Bellagio VI, 1974 March 19 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - "National Agricultural Systems", Conference on Agricultural Education in Developing Nations, Bellagio, Italy, 1974 March 11-15 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Fellowship and Scholarship Report, 1974 March 8 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - "International Implications for Programs in Agricultural Education", Atlanta, GA, 1974 February 11 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - "New Era in Crop Improvement", Herbert Kendall Hayes Memorial Lecture, St. Paul, MN, 1974 February 5, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - "Extending the Green Revolution", World Development, Vol. 1 No. 12, 1973 December (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - "International Agricultural Research Institute: Their Unique Capabilities", 10th Anniversary Convocation of International Rice Research Institute, 1972 April 20-21 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - "Meeting World Needs for Agricultural Technology", and Summary, Bellagio II, 1970 February 3-6 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - "Challenges to Agricultural Scientists", The American Phytopathological Society, Spokane, WA, 1969 August 20 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - "Strengthening National Agricultural Research and Development Systems", 1969 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - "Meeting Protein Needs Through Plant Breeding, Getting the Job Done", American Society of Agronomy Meeting, New Orleans, LA, 1968 November 12 (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - "Expanding Food Production in Hungry Nations: The Promise, The Problems", The American Assembly, Harriman, NY, 1968 October 31-November 3 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - "Agricultural College: Their Greatest Challenge", Columbus, OH, 1967 November 14 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - "Intensification of Crop Production", National Academy of Sciences-National Research Council, Washington, D. C., 1967 May 9 (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - "World Food Problem: Myths and Musts", 1967 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - "The Crop Production Equation", The Weed Society of America, Washington, D. C., 1967 February 13-16 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - "Approaches to the World Food Problem", Southwest Agricultural Forum, Tulsa, OK, 1967 January 19 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - "Making Agronomy Serve Developing Countries", American Society of Agronomy, Stillwater, OK, 1966 August 21-26 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - "Rice Research: A Race Against Time", International Rice Research Institute, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Trip Report, Plant Studies Delegation to the People's Republic of China, 1974 August 27-September 23 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Plant Studies in the People's Republic of China: A Trip Report of the American Plant Studies Delegation, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - "A First Report on Agricultural and Rural Development in the Republic of China", 1980 July 12 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Publications and Speeches, Part I of IV, 1964-1968 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - Publications and Speeches, Part II of IV, 1968-1974 (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Publications and Speeches, Part III of IV, 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Publications and Speeches, Part IV of IV, 1976-1978 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Oral History, Rockefeller Foundation Program in Agriculture, Interview with Sterling Wortman, 1966 August 2, 4 (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - "The Case for a "Development College"" (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - "SUNY: A Tenth Dimension", Conference on International Programs and Activities, Albany, NY, 1979 November 1 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - "The Technological Basis for Intensified Agriculture", 1969 April 23-15 (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - Economic Impact, A Quarterly Review of World Economics, No. 32, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line (Box 11, Folder 124-125)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Notes and Correspondence, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 2: Danger Signals in America?, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 4: The Economic Frontier, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 128)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 5: Expanding the World Economy, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 129)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 6: Free Enterprise and America's Future, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 130)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 7: U. S. Agriculture: How Strong?, 1974, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 131)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 8: Challenges from Abroad, 1979-1981 (Box 11, Folder 132)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 9: Toward Greater U. S. Competitiveness (Box 11, Folder 133)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 10: Official Assistance & Private Cooperation, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 134)
  - Beyond the Bottom Line, Chapter 11: Beyond the Bottom Line, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 135)